by default almost
every storage class provisioner trying
to get my words
right defaults to delete reclaim
policy and what that means is that every
one of these I this is very confusing
because this is PVC it's not it's a it
is this is a PV this is a persistent
volume that has been dynamically
allocated for this specific PVC and this
specific PVC only the most important
difference between a physical persistent
volume and a persistent volume claim is
where they live and where they're
managed the persistent volume is a
cluster level
resource and therefore you have to be
able to do cluster things you have to
have admin rights and all that kind of
thing which is why most of the storage
class providers dynamically create them
because otherwise the person creating
the PBC C which lives in the name space
it's in the user name space area so so
this is where you're always seeing pbc's
get created by people that are making
applications and deploying them and
things it's a totally different
permission scope right so the reason
these storage classes are set up to
automatically create a persistent volume
is because if not you'd they'd have to
trouble the admins or whoever and have
them go create a persistent volume for
everyone therefore what you end up
getting is you're getting you end up in
most clusters on Pam and elsewhere in
the clatter and stuff you end up getting
a a storage class
default which is very you know painless
and what that says is okay your storage
is not going to survive undeploying your
namespace or taking it down deleting
your namespace and that means that your
storage is ephemeral just like your
containers I I really really really want
to hit on this point this is probably
the most important thing at old guy like
me had to really Bang into his head to
understand storage is ephemeral in
kubernetes by default that means it
doesn't hang around your story most
kubernetes systems are set up so that
everything is slash
temp to use a reference from the old
days I I know someone's going to yell at
me because they're going to be pedantic
about because why because it's just easy
because if they didn't do that you'd
have to go through all the management of
you know creating a p a persistent
volume for everybody who ever wanted to
use a
dis in in the kubernetes cluster and
then the whole point of it being able to
be used would be hard why does this
matter because watch what happens when I
undeploy the PVC and let let me give you
a very specific very very specific case
here so I found this because I was
testing backing up the database so so
here you see this physical volume has
got PG dumps all these PG dumps I turned
it up to 1 minute so I can see them all
happening and so these are my database
backups this very rather important that
I have database backups around and what
I'm about to show you is that all these
backups are going to be deleted
automatically and this is very
scary so this is very very scary because
the whole point of the backup is to be
able to come back and get it again right
well here here is here this right now
I'm on another so this is the harbor
this is I told you I have two storage
classes right so I just switched storage
classes I switched to use the new one I
explicitly am using the new one which
has a policy of retain because I'm
testing what happens when you delete a
physical volum when you delete a PVC or
you you know indirectly by you know
undeploying your entire name space in
this case Harbor so so let's go you
might have to pause this video and watch
it several times because it's very
complicated so there here's all my this
is a working Harbor instance it's
absolutely beautiful it totally works
it's running its backups uh the zero
doesn't mean not ready by the way that
means it's a job or a crown job this is
actually a big annoyance of mine that
this is running but it does technically
it's not running because it was a crown
job therefore it doesn't ever get a one
here which means it looks like it's
broken already even though it's not it's
absolutely not it's totally clean and
healthy it always was even though
worried me so Harbor Post is the one we
were looking at and the the dump these
dump jobs are the things that are
creating those dump files in the PVC
right so this this is a working running
bitnami Harbor chart that has been that
installed and you can go look at my my
my RBX Rob SL uh K k8s app- Harbor if
you want to see how I'm doing this
because I I want to have Arbor in my own
uh environment at home and I'm also
testing a deployment at work so
so this all looks well and good right
everything is running the PBS are being
created Dynam the files are being
created in in the physical volume by
themselves but let me let's look take a
look at the pbcs get PBC whoops K get
PVC and here you can see you've got all
the pbcs right and you can see that
they're they're using the dcz storage
class and here is the actual volume so
this is even though it's got PBC in the
name that's because that persistent
volume was created for this and only
this PVC that's what the rwo means the
rwo means that nobody gets access to
this to this storage except for this uh
anything that's that's binding to this
right to this to this PBC this is very
very you know exclusive there's not a
lot of things going on there that means
this this physical uh this persistent
volume is only visible
I mean only accessible to this that's
all now I there is a level of
complication here you could actually
share uh a physical volume across
multiple PVCs and and uh I haven't
played around with that option because
that does require an entirely different
Source cost but the reason we're looking
at this is I want you to see that I mean
some of this stuff can go away right
like we need a temporary disc space to
like have the datab to have the server
run and put our configuration files in
there and and maybe write some caching
and stuff like that so so most of the
time you know obliterating the storage
for a running deployment a running pod
is fine most of the time that's fine and
that's why kubernetes defaults to this
but sometimes it's not and I want you to
see what how it's not so I mean it goes
without saying that these
databases uh backups are important right
I mean that's the whole reason I did
this the whole point is to keep these
databases here and I'm going to I'm
about to conclude here and show you
unless you have copied these specific
files out of this directory and onto
another stateful system of some kind
they are going to get blown away when
you try to just reconfigure or change
your namespace or undeploy so I have an
un here's my deploy script my deploy
script just you know just after we
flatten a template out we just do apply
you can look at all that and that's the
thing that builds up the new the new
application and and then we have this
undeploy this is pretty common across
all our applications and then we have
this undeploy right okay I'm just going
to delete all those manifests which
include the Nam space right um one of
the one of the manifests that is written
here uh is the namespace
itself
and so if you delete the it's very very
common to delete a
namespace uh I actually just realized
there might be something I could do
differently here rather than delete Nam
space I could delete all the pieces of
it but not but leave the name space
around let me say show you why because
but that's very uncommon the the common
thing is to just delete the entire Nam
space because the Nam space is supposed
to be sort of the whole grouped together
application right and that's what it's
doing so so then I do undeploy here and
it's going to it's going to take a
little while it's going to delete all
these things um
but but Watch What Happens over here so
now we do the
tree and you'll see over time actually
this is I used to have this on a
watch here so you can see that they're
all gone they're all going away and now
they're all dead so every single one of
those temporary PVCs those temporary
persistent volumes which if you think
about it is kind of ass backwards really
right I mean why call it a a persistent
volume if it's not if it only persists
as long as the application is around
that doesn't sound very persistent to me
at all right so so that's a pretty bad
thing um I just lost all my backups so
you better hope you have a copy of
them right it gets worse though in in
our production environment we have a 15
terabytes of container registry storage
where all the containers that are sub
the images that are submitted to to
Harbor are stored on
disk now if I you know if I had had
deployed this I would have just lost all
15 terabytes of that data and you can't
really back that up easily right so what
is the solution here this is what we're
testing and I'm going to show you at
least my initial attempt and I'll
probably end the video here so I can do
some more uh work on this but the main
Crux of this video had just happened
when I undeployed the resour that name
space when I undeleted the aace and
everything that went with it including
PBC because why because PBC is a nam
spaced resource PB is not PB is is
cluster level PVC is nam Space level
those two are
different and they might seem like
they're the same because usually the PV
is being dynamically allocated like I
just showed you but that's not always
the case you can specifically create a
storage class and and I assigned to that
or you can specifically create a PV and
changes parameters in in a storage even
in the same old storage C so right now
I'm experimenting with that right like
and and I don't know I don't know what's
going to happen here so let's go ahead
and deploy using uh we're going to
deploy uh the re the Manifest I just
built uh and we're going to take a peek
and see what happens so this is going to
start spinning up um wait where are we
we on Harbor we need to go back to
uh we want to go back where's NFS Harbor
here we go okay so here we are watching
the same directory on Harbor now and um
NFS Harbor right so we can close this
one wait okay this is interesting so we
still have some PB popping up on NFA
Kates but we also have stuff popping up
on Harbor on a different storage class
so we have stuff in two places I have
two NFS two NFS exports two NFS mounts
that are simulating two different
storage classes and the you can see it
up here uh you can see that this is the
case one this is the this is the
dynamically allocated storage a PBC and
you can see that the backups are not on
this one right I mean it it you can't
really tell that right here but it you
will be able to it'll start writing it
right so actually let's go in and change
um let's go in and change that so we're
going to change uh K edit uh oh gosh
let's see
let's let's edit the
uh the job is it a job I can't remember
what it is I think it's the crown job
yeah Crown job Cron job batch har okay
let's go change this from
hourly uh to minute two three four five
all right so so that's been changed uh K
get pods so there you see the pods are
almost all up job service is the last
one they come up in E core
and uh we'll start to
see uh the the the backup kick off
probably at the top of the hour here so
let's actually do this let's do watch
Das to get bus I it's my favorite
there's other ways to do
this um and we're just going to watch
this until a backup shows up so here's
the K app this stuff is largely not
going to change this is you know
configuration files and and uh actually
the trivy stuff um I think uh I think
this one down the bottom here is where
the registry is going to be is going to
go and frankly in my testing I should
probably create an automatic image
creation into Harbor uh as a part
there's a whole you know system
integration test Suite that I'm starting
to work on as well a bunch of scripts to
to actually see how this stuff is all
working and and I'll be making videos
about that later but okay so we have our
backup execute op so nothing changed in
the NFS Kates but we we pointed the
backups at the other storage class so
let's look at that um that is where is
it is this it
no uh oh here it is okay so so there we
go there's our dump right so we got our
PG dump is now storing it in you know a
completely different Mount Point uh in
this case it's a different machine even
uh that a version machine that has
exported NFS Harbor now this is where
things are going to get interesting now
what happens when there's two we get one
every minute so um now incidentally we
have it set to only show three uh we
have a un fail and success the only keep
three around thing if you don't know
what I mean um okay so there's our
storage Vol yeah we can go ahead and
close this one uh what else we got so
okay here's our pods so there there'll
only ever be three of these things that
say completed um because of of a setting
I can't remember right now it's
something on success and failure that's
just to show you the last jobs that ran
so you can go in there and see check on
them and see what they're doing um it
doesn't save jobs the the pods that are
created for jobs are not retained um and
and if make sure you set that by the way
because if you don't set that you will
blast out your container Engine with
with a bunch of of of defunct job pods
um and anyway so so you know it's been
running for a while and we've got our
stuff here uh there's our dumps we got
several dumps in here okay so since this
storage class once again is is uh wait
what oh right bad Mac that's a different
thing uh I kind of got stuff all over I
should probably label it better what is
this is this Kate's yeah let's label
this better let's label this
uh NFS
Kates so we can see and then NFS Harbor
all right so we have Z Anis Harbor and
then we have the actual Harbor installer
thing and uh d f okay so K get pods I
mean you can see that K get by the way
here's here's the cluster itself uh it's
I mean my M clusters just three control
planes and three workers
um
and all right so K get
SC uh so they they're completed they're
remov from the container time yep they
just keep around so you can describe
them look it
looks
uh so they're they kept in SD by the
containers taken out really I did not
know that so LBG is just saying in the
chat that um that the that after a job
or crown job completes that the actual
container is is got immediately gotten
rid of but it just keeps the information
around about it incd which is this kuber
database so you can go look at what
happened and stuff that's interesting
okay I did not know that um so again
here are the two storage classes we
created the only difference between them
uh is the reclaim policy and we're about
to test what happens when I
undeploy uh all of that stuff you saw
how that deleted the physical Vol the
persistent volumes when I did it uh with
a retame with a Rec policy of delete but
I I don't know what's going to happen I
honestly don't know so let's try it out
um so we're going to undeploy again this
is just deleting the whole thing and uh
we can kind of watch it in real
time uh let's watch this in real time so
I'm suspecting this this class is going
to stay up and this one this one's going
to go away so this one we watch is being
deleted and then this one is being
retained which is what we would expect
right uh PBC before you delete it
uh PBC dump the
PBC we don't need to dump the PBC I
don't need to do that I have it I have
them manifest for already so so there we
go
um so so you can see that by changing
the storage class policy
to retain I got to show you that again
myself again by changing the recing
policy to retain on this storage class
and by explicitly telling the backups to
use that storage class you'll notice
that other stuff in this particular
deployment you know application did not
right it used the default uh temporary
ephemeral sort of storage and but by
changing so there it is and but by
changing it to use uh this other one
these database backups were
saved uh you don't have the additional
medic case add added to bind it to the
PB right so um so and that and that's
kind of the next part of this so the
part the next part is well okay we got
our database backups they didn't get
taken out um but then that remain then
the question remains well what do we do
with these backups okay the backups are
still there the the volumes haven't been
deleted uh they're not going anywhere
but now they're really not going
anywhere unless you explicitly get rid
of them right and and so actually one of
the things that I want to look at now is
is this and this is LBG is kind of
hinting at this so if you do
um if if we're we're going to do a k get
um K get PV not PVC this time and you'll
see that there are still
volumes that are in the uh Harbor that
well they're they they're in the they're
on the Harbor storage class but uh
somebody was saying I should we should
dump them before you delete the before
you undeploy you should actually save
out the name of the physical the
persistent volume so that you know which
one went with your last running version
of your because you lose all reference
to that um but it's still there right so
this particular case it's not hard for
me to figure out it's the only one left
right and and there could be an argument
made that it's really not as important
to know in this case because these are
dated right so if you know the content
of the pp the you know you can go back I
mean this is this is a very precise case
because I just need a copy of the of the
flat back backup that's it I don't I
don't need and frankly I only need the
last one right so I can keep these
things running around and then I'll I'll
get one of these sort of crazily named
now why is it named that because it was
still dynamically allocated it was still
dynamically allocated that's why the
name has got that weird identifier in it
so it's Unique it doesn't crunch you
know crunch back up it doesn't just you
disagree with something and then you get
all of this PG dump data in here so
potentially you know it it would be nice
to to put in my undeploy oh hey don't
forget that your dumps are over here
still you know what I mean and this case
right but in order to get this retain
policy for this we we need to do this so
so this this has been a very short video
to just it's relatively long but it's a
short video to to just to say one thing
the one I just all I want to show is one
thing that you can have exactly the same
storage class and you can have uh one of
them be the reclaim policy of delete and
one of them retain and if you set it to
delete the underlying data will never
never be deleted by
kubernetes and for somebody who might
want that um yeah we need image storage
backup we we talked about that at the
beginning of the video that's coming
that's also going to be added so so
that's kind of taking us to the next
point so the the the takeaway from this
video is is one thing if you use the
default you're going to get burned
you're going to get burned
because it for this kind of thing you're
going to you're going to reset you're
going to clear your name space it's all
very common things that people do all
the time during management and your your
your files will be gone because they're
going to get cleaned up because it was
essentially temp because the retain
policy was not set and in order to get a
retain policy you have to have a
specific storage class created that does
that and then when you do that you have
to give very very limited access to that
because anybody that you allow to
create uh pbcs against the retained
storage class you need to like babysit
that yourself now not only do you have
to babysit it and make sure people don't
leave it around because you're going to
burn up all your disc and they're not
going to clean it up right but you also
have to be able to make sure you know
what PBC what you know what was the name
of it from the last one that ran so at
that point it becomes kind of a question
of okay what's easier is it is it easier
for me to set up a a part of the crown
job something that you know scps over
the PG dump file to something else and
in the case of PG dump files that's
probably okay the size of them is not
too big um you know they're not big but
that does kind of somebody mentioned it
already uh uh so all the time like on
upgrade you would definitely run it
uninstall so um so when I mean you
undeploy and then you deploy a new one
you never just leave the thing around
that's that's the nature of like
managing your kubernetes applications
you got to be able to do that in order
up to to build a somebody asked about
something else I'm getting distracted so
um but but so in this case in the case
of the PG dump files these these these
SQL files are relatively small and
adding a file transfer to a stateful
storage system outside kubernetes scope
uh is going to be a good thing to do
that's going to be something that we
could totally do and it would be really
easy but what about the 15
terabytes of image registry storage
right what about that how do you back
that up right now if somebody
uninstalled Harbor or undeployed Harbor
and deleted the name space for for
Harbor in our kubernetes cluster which
is a very common the modern way to do
clusters is not to leave things around
forever it's it's to be able to bring up
and tear down tear up bring up and tear
down your applications very easily the
whole cicd kind of idea now that it gets
hard when you got 15 terab of storage
you got to figure out some kind of
exception to that rule but being able to
just run undeploy and deploy and have it
be essentially the same as a container a
FAL and have it not and have it just
work is a big part of that but then you
have to be really conscious of the stuff
that you absolutely want to persist
beyond beyond a deploy and an undeploy
so so those are th those are the ways
that we are going to go about doing it
one of the solutions and this is why I
mentioned the registry thing is if you
have 15 terabytes in a thing
then you definitely want to be able to
keep that around that was something you
probably never ever want to delete uh
the you know it just wouldn't in fact
but then then it becomes a matter of
well how do you
reassociate uh that with the other
things so so let's say so a disaster
recovery scenario in that case would be
that you would so you tear down your
cluster uh your your application and
then you bring your application back and
then you look up what that PVC is either
or it's part of your tear down process
you write it out someplace to a file so
you know the name and then you
reassociate that name you rebind that
name uh that storage class to PVC so so
that you don't lose that 15 terabytes
all right um and uh that's the end of
that video